<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Orders taken &amp; enacted, for orphans and their portions. Anno M D. LXXX.</title>
            <title>Acts and orders. 1580</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16708</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105583</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841310</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841310</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06224)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 573:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Orders taken &amp; enacted, for orphans and their portions. Anno M D. LXXX.</title>
                  <title>Acts and orders. 1580</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. East] for Gabriel Cawood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1580]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Orders enacted for orphanes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Orphans --  England --  London --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5885:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5885:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Orders taken &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, for Orphans and their portions.</p>
            <p>Anno MD. LXXX.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for Gabriel Cawood.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5885:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5885:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Orders enacted.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>AD Commune concilium, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tum in Guildhaldia ciuitatis Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dini. <date>xiii. die Octob. Anno regni Eduardi ſex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</date> Dei gratia Angliae, Franciae &amp; Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berniae Regis, fidei defenſoris, &amp; in terra Eccleſiae Anglicanae, &amp; Hiberni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae ſupremicapitis, quinto: coram An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drea Iudde Milite, tunc Maiore, &amp; Aldremannis Ciuitatis illius, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt inter alia, inactitata, conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa &amp; ſtabilita, omnia &amp; ſingula ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentia.</dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie sof <hi>London,</hi> is of late yeres ſore decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and dayly is lyke to decaye, more and more: A great cauſe &amp; occaſion whereoff among other, hath ben, for that frée mens children, (Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes of the ſayd Citie) ſometimes in the lyues of their Parents, and ſometimes after their deceaſes, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lefte wealthy and rich, doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow themſelues in vngodly Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,
<pb facs="tcp:5885:3"/>for the moſt part in their young age, at their owne wills &amp; pleaſures, without the conſent and againſt the mindes of their friends, ſaying &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, that the Law &amp; cuſtome of the ſaid Citie giueth vnto them their portions, whether they mary by the aſſent of their friends or not, &amp; ſo do daily caſt away &amp; vndoe themſelues, in truſt to haue their ſaide portions, whether their parents or frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds will or will not. And therby doe they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow themſelues vpon ſimple &amp; light perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, hauing neither cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſubſtance, ne good or honeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. By reaſon where-of<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch Orphanes, inordinately, &amp; inſolently, do ſpende &amp; conſume their patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; portions in ſhort time, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the vndoing of themſelues, and to the great ignomie &amp; ſhame of their friends, but alſo to the great ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Lord Maior &amp; Aldermen of this citie (who bene reputed &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as Fathers &amp; Protectors of the ſame Orphanes) &amp; to the great loſſe and hinderaunce of the ſayd Citie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:5885:3"/>
And foraſmuch as the ſayd Lord Maior and Citizens; haue by theyr lawes, and cuſtomes, power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to make lawes and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by their common counſaile, for redreſſe of the ſame. It is therefore now (to the intent to reduce the ſame to a more godly, more profitable and decent order and conformitie) by the ſaid Lord Maior, and Communaltie, and Citizens, in this preſent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon counſayle aſſembled, and by aucthoritye of the ſame common Counſaile, enacted, ordeined, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, &amp; eſtabliſhed for a Law perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be obſerued &amp; kept within the ſaid Citie. That if any Orphane, or child of anye frée man or frée wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of the ſayd Citie doe offend in any the things héereafter expreſſed, and be thereoff lawfully conuicted, afore the Lorde Maior and the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen or els where, that then they and euery of them, ſhall to al entents purpoſes, conſtructions &amp; meanings; be vnabled and barred to demaund and claime their portion or portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb facs="tcp:5885:4"/>&amp; alſo ſhal loſe &amp; forgoe &amp; be barred for euer, of all and euery his, hir, or their part or parts, &amp; portions to him or them belonging, by and after the death of his or their ſaid father or mother, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goods &amp; cattalles, of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch father &amp; mother, by reaſon of any Law, cuſtome, ordinance, vſage, fraunches, priuiledge, act of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune counſale, or other thing, héeretofore had or vſed, within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Citie. The ſame Law, Cuſtome, Ordinaunce, or other thing whatſoeuer, heeretofore had, made, ordeined, allowed, &amp; put in vre, to the contrarye in anye wiſe notwithſtanding. That is to wit. Firſt, if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>child, or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>child, ſhal malitiouſly go about or attempt to do, or cauſe to be done, any bodily harme, death, or deſtruction to his or their Father or Mother: Or if any manchilde do héerafter mary or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract mariage in the life of his father or mother (by whom he will clayme any portion) vnder the age of xxi. yeres, without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſent of his ſayd Father, or Mother, by whom hée
<pb facs="tcp:5885:4"/>will claime any portion: Or if any womanchilde doe héereafter mary or contract mariage, in the life of hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or other parent, by whom ſhe ſhall claime any portion, before the age of xviii. yeares, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of hir Father, or ſuch other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by whome ſhee ſhall or maye claime any portion: Or if any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>childe bée a Thiefe, or a Fellon, or a common whore haunter, a common Diſer, or a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon player at vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full games notoriouſly known: Or if any womanchilde ſhal héerafter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any whoredome, or be a common Picker, that then euery of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſons ſo offending, ſhalbe barred &amp; excluded to haue, or demaund any portion.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwayes, that it ſhalbe lawful, for the father, or mother of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch childe, or children, to giue &amp; bequeath in Legacie, to ſuch childe or children, as much as the portion of ſuch child ſo, offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſhal amou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by the cuſtome of the ſaid citie and then ſuch childe therby to be enabled to haue, &amp; demaund the ſame, as por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:5885:5"/>this Act, notwithſtanding, ſo that the ſame Legacie be conteined in his or their teſtament in writing, &amp; not otherwiſe. And that then, and from thenceforth, his ſaid childe, or childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be admitted and reſtored to claime ſuch legacie, or legacies, in ſuch ſort, manner &amp; forme, as if there had bon neuer any ſuch offence done, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by any ſuch childe.</p>
            <p>Item, it is further ordeined, enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, authorized and eſtabliſhed, by the authoritie aforeſaid, that if any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manchilde, being an Orphane, &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the age of. xxi. yeares, at any time héerafter, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of hir father, do enſure or contract hir ſelfe in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or els according to the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical lawes of this Realine, do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſolempnize or conſumate Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, with any frée man of this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the conſent &amp; agréeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this ſayd ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Lond<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> for the time being, not obteined &amp; had, that then for euerye ſuch default &amp; offence committed or done, by any Orphane or Orphanes,
<pb facs="tcp:5885:5"/>of the ſayde Citie, the ſame béeinge confeſſed or ſufficientlye proued by two witneſſes, or otherwiſe before the ſaid Lorde Mayre and Aldermen of this ſayde Citie of <hi>London,</hi> for the time béeing, at and in a Court of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, ſhe or they that ſo happen to behaue hir or themſelues, as is afore ſayde, ſhall forfeit, forgoe and looſe. ij. d of and for euery pound, ſo due or to be due vnto hir, or the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by reaſon of any ſuch Orphanage, the ſumme of. xij. d. of euery. li. to goe, or to be to the vſe of the chamber of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd citie, according to the auncient cuſtome before this time, in ſuch caſe vſed. And if the ſaid contract or mariage of the ſayde Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan or Orphans, be made with any forrein, not being frée of this Citie, at the time of any ſuch contract or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage made, that then the ſayd Ophan or Orphans, and euery of them ſhall forfait and looſe. iij. s. of euery pound, or to be due vnto hir or them, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of any Orphanage or cuſtome had and vſed within the ſayd Citie. The one ſhilling of the ſayd, iij. s. of euerye
<pb facs="tcp:5885:6"/>pound, to go, or to be, to the vſe of the chamber of the ſayd citie, in ſuch ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp; forme as is aforeſaid. And the other. tj. s. ſo forfeited of euery pound, to go to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of ſuch other Orphane, or Orphanes, as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal remain vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maried. Or els for default of ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes, or Orphane, to remain to the next of the kinred of the Orphane ſo offending.</p>
            <p>Alſo be it further ordeined, enacted, &amp; eſtabliſhed by authoritie aforeſayd, for, &amp; in eſchewing of diuers varie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, contentions, &amp; ſutes, that dayly héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore haue, &amp; héereafter may enſue: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any frée mans childe, man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man fortune to be maried héereafter, in the life time of his, or their father, by his conſent, &amp; not fully aduaunced off, &amp; to his, or hir full part, or porcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of his, or hir, ſayd Fathers goods, as he ſhalbe worth at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of his diſeaſe, according to the auncient lawes and cuſtomes, of this ſayd Citie: that then euery ſuch frée mans childe, ſo béeing maryed in the life time of his, or hir Father ſhalbe to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes,
<pb facs="tcp:5885:6"/>diſabled to demaunde any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er part or porcion, of his or hir fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers goods, after the diſeaſe of his, or <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir father, but ſhalbe adiudged, repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be fully aduanced, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ording as the lawe and cuſtome of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his citie, hath bene long time out of minde, except his or hir ſayd father, do mencion certainly in his laſt will, or <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtament, or by other writing ſigned with his own proper name, or marke <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he certeintie of the ſum or ſums of money, goods and cattells, &amp; the value of them that the Father gaue, payed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r departed withall, or otherwiſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſured or héereafter ſhall giue, paye, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epart withall, or otherwiſe make aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urance off, vnto him, or hir, before at <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r after the mariage of him or hir, or <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>therwiſe in his lyfe time, for and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes their aduauncements, in the name of his, or hir part, or portion.</p>
            <p>And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery ſuch Orphane, or childe which after the deceaſe of his or hir ſayd Father, can bring foorth the ſayd Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or other writing ſigned or marked with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fathers hand or mark,
<pb facs="tcp:5885:7"/>wherein the certeintie of ſuch mone<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> goodes, or Cattells, as they haue o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhall haue receiued of their ſayd Fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, or by the ſame father, aſſured b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eſpecialtie, or otherwiſe ſhal haue a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much of the ready money, goods, cat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tells, and debtes, of the ſayd Father as (with that which he or they ſhal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue receiued towards their aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ments, in the life of their ſaid father ſhall make vp a full childes part, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his goods and Cattells, as he ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worth at the time of his deceaſe. Th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſame to be demaunded, aſked, &amp; clay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, or ſued for againſt the executor or executors, adminiſtratour, or ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miniſtratours, of the goods, and Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells of the ſayd Father, by bill Ori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ginall, to be commenced to our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reigne Lord, the kings court, holden in the vtter chamber of the guild-hal<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the ſayd citie, before the ſayd Lord Mayre and Aldermen of the ſame ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the time béeing, any law or cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtome, héeretofore made, or vſed to th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> contrary, notwithſtanding. In which action, no wager of Lawe, or Eſſoine.
<pb facs="tcp:5885:7"/>ſhalbe admitted, or allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway and it is further <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nacted, that if anye frée mans ſonne, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>éeing of full age (which ſhall heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be maried with the conſent of his father, or any other perte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being of ful age, which ſhall héereafter mary any frée mans daughter) doe at the time of the eſpouſalls, or anye time after, confeſſe themſelues, by writing fully ſatiſfied, of his, or their portion, or doo otherwiſe acquite and diſcharge, the Father of ſuch frée mans ſounes, or daughters, of all their part and por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, due, or to be due, by the Lawe and cuſtome of the Citie, that then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſuch perſon, ſo confeſſing, acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or otherwiſe diſcharging, ſhalbe reputed and taken, as fully aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, of his, or theyr whole part, or por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; ſhal not be enabled, to demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d any further, or greater part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, goods, &amp; cattells, of his or hir Father: this law, or any other law or cuſtome héeretofore had, made, or vſed to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And further, for as much as it is
<pb facs="tcp:5885:8"/>thought very preiudicial &amp; hurtful the fatherleſſe children &amp; Orphane when the mother, or mother in law being executrix of the laſt wil &amp; teſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of hir late huſband, by whom after whoſe death, the Orphanes a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> intituled to an Orphanage, (acco<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to the ſayd laudable cuſtomes <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this citie) doe diuers times marry <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> contract matrimony, ſome with for<gap reason="illegible" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, &amp; perſons vnknowne, &amp; ſome <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Free men, or euer a iuſt Inuentory <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the goods, cattels, plate, Iuells, re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy money of the Teſtatours, be by t<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> brought in: By reaſon wheroff, man<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times, they (either for feare or affect<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of their huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, or for ſome othe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſiniſter cauſe) doe bring in very ſuſp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tious Inuentories, omittinge there<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> either ready money, Plate, Iuells, o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> debts, or ſome other thing, or things whereby ſome benefit ſhould redoun<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the fatherleſſe children, to the grea<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loſſe and hinderance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Orphane<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſometime ſlaunder to the Lord Mayre, and Aldermen of the Citie notwithſtanding their great care, an<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:5885:8"/>trauaile that they take for the good ordering, and true aunſwering of the ſayd Orphanes.</p>
            <p>It is therefore, by lyke authoritie, ordeined, eſtabliſhed, and enacted, that if after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt day of Nouember next enſuing, any widow, which is, or ſhall be made executrix of the Teſtament and laſt will of hir late huſband, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a frée man) or ſhall take vpon hir the adminiſtration of the goods, &amp; cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells, of hir late huſbande (béeing a free man) doe not vpon hir othe bring in, and exhibit, or cauſe to be brought in, &amp; exhibited before the Lord Mayre, and Aldermen of this ſayd Citie, for the time being at, and in a court of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, a iuſt and perfect Inuentory (to their knowledge,) of all the goods, cattells, plate, and Iuells, ready mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and debts, as were hir ſayd huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of his death, appray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed according to the law of the ſaid ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, before ſhe do enſure hir ſelf in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or contract mariage, or els ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the lawes of the Realme, doe perfectly ſolemnize, or conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mate
<pb facs="tcp:5885:9"/>mariage with any perſon, before ſuch time as aforeſaid, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo offending, ſhall forfait and looſe viij s. of euery pound, of hir portion, of the goods of hir late huſband, due to hir by the laudable cuſtome of this ſayd Citie, the ſame to go to the vſe of ſuch Orphane, or Orphanes, as then ſhalbe entituled to haue or demaund any Orphanage, or portion, after the death of his or hir late Father, the ſame to be demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, aſked, claimed, or ſued for, againſt ſuche executrix, or adminiſtratrix, by bil original of debt, to be commenced, in our Souereigne Lord the kinges Court, holden in the vtter chamber of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Guild-hall, of the ſaid citie, before the Lord Mayre, and Aldermen of the ſame Citie, for the time béeing, any law, &amp;c. In which Action, no wager. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Eaſt, for Gabriel Cawood.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5885:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
